Finding Aid for University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization (University of Michigan) records, 1964-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization (University of Michigan) records 1964-1979
University of Michigan. University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization.
91470 Bimu C565 2
Committee files consisting of reports, correspondence, minutes, and subject files; also files relating to Educom, a corporation established to promote collaboration in the development, operation, and use of technology in higher education and research.
4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor No. 7887 ) was transferred in 1991. 7887
The record group is open for research without restriction.
The University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization (UCCPU) was established in 1965. The UCCPU was founded on the recommendation of the Ad Hoc Computing Advisory Committee. The Ad Hoc Committee was set up to advise the vice president for research on the use of computers at the University of Michigan and was operational during 1964. Donald Katz was chairman of the committee and in turn became chairman of UCCPU. The UCCPU was composed of faculty members appointed from many units of the university for varying terms. The charge to UCCPU was to create policies for the university to adopt in matters relating to the selection, use, management, and potential use of computers in university programs of instruction and research. Although the committee was responsible for the three University of Michigan campuses, the majority of activity centered on computing at the Ann Arbor campus. The most important work of the committee was overseeing the change from a monolithic central computing center to a distributed network system of computing.
The first concern of UCCPU was to address the recommendations found in the Ad Hoc Committee's 1964 "Report on Machine Computation at the University." They included enlarging the central computing facility and acquiring a computer with online capabilities. UCCPU reviewed the bids received at the end of 1964 for a new computer. Its recommendation was to lease an International Business Machines (IBM) system 360 model 66m to be operational by 1967. This new system provided greatly expanded memory and online capabilities. At the same time the Michigan Terminal System (MTS) was created by the University's Computing Center to function as the operating system on the new IBM.
The committee also developed a policy to evaluate proposals for the acquisition of computing equipment or services. The goal was to maintain high standards of computing capabilities, in a cost effective manner, for the university as a whole. In addition, the committee undertook various surveys of computer equipment on campus, while looking at the future needs of the many units within the university.
The surveys aided the committee in meeting another of its charges, that of providing long-range planning and allocation recommendations for the orderly expansion of computing resources at the university. Originally, this charge only covered the Computing Center, the mission of which was educational and research computing. The center also examined university participation in implementing and overseeing educational computing networks such as Merit and EDUCOM. Merit is a computer network of Michigan universities that has been operational since 1971. EDUCOM is a non-profit corporation founded in 1964 by W. N. Hubbard, Jr., Alexander Barry, and James G. Miller, three faculty members at the University of Michigan. It was designed to promote collaboration in the development, operation, and use of technology in higher education and research. Emphasis was placed on computer technology, particularly networking, as a means of sharing physical and intellectual resources. A prototype computer network was organized by EDUCOM in 1975 with National Science Foundation grant support. EDUCOM also offers other services to member institutions such as discounts on computer hardware.
UCCPU's charge was enlarged in 1972 to create a planning strategy for the future of computing at the university. The 1970s brought many advances in computer technology to which the committee had to respond. The most important of these changes was the introduction of minicomputers. Traditionally all computing at the Ann Arbor campus occurred on the main frame computer located at the Computing Center. The minicomputer allowed for autonomous computers within individual units. Another technological change challenging the autonomy of the computing center was the emergence of computer networks. The committee tried to steer a middle ground between the use of a central computing facility and minicomputers. As part of this work, various subcommittees were established to study the impact of the minicomputer on campus. Software policy and computer ethics also were concerns during the 1970s as the production of software increased. In addition, the committee's charge of long-range planning and oversight was expanded. It began to oversee the Data Services Center, which was responsible for administrative computing, and the Hospital Data Services Center, which was created in 1974.
From the time of its establishment, UCCPU reported to the vice president for research, A. Geoffrey Norman until 1972 and Charles G. Overberger from 1972 to 1983. Donald L. Katz was the first chairman of the committee and served from 1965 to 1971. Gordon Nordby was his replacement and served until 1977. At the same time, Nordby also served in various positions with EDUCOM. UCCPU was disbanded in 1985 when the university's Information Technology Division was created.
The records of the University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization (4 linear feet) cover the years from 1964 to 1979 and include reports, correspondence, minutes, and subject files. The records are divided into two series, Committee Files and EDUCOM Files. The records in both series are arranged in alphabetical order by topic.
Subjects:
Computers.; Educom.; Universities and colleges--Data processing.; University of Michigan. Computing Center.; University of Michigan. University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization.
- Committee Files
  The Committee Files series (3.5 linear feet) consists of records detailing all aspects of the committee's work from 1964 to 1979. The Ad Hoc Computing Advisory Committee folder documents the predecessor to the UCCPU, and includes a section of its 1964 report (Machine Computation at the University of Michigan). A major part of the documentation in this series is composed of requests for computer purchases from various departments of the university. The minutes contain committee members' evaluations of the requests and, prior to 1971, the requests themselves are included in the minutes. The majority of computer requests came during the 1970s, however, and are found in folders marked Computer Requests.
  The Correspondence files include communication between the vice president for research, the chairman of the committee, members of the committee, and university faculty. The minutes provide a comprehensive look at the changing issues faced by the committee. The minutes folders also contain valuable background materials on the issues discussed at each meeting.
  The Dearborn files document long-range planning for that campus, particularly the concern over whether to create a stand-alone Data Systems Center or connect with the Data Systems Center in Ann Arbor. The Flint files document the development of the computer resources at the Flint campus, and primarily relate to the 1974 proposal to create a communications link with Ann Arbor to the Computing Center and the Data Systems Center.
  The Hierarchical Computing at the University of Michigan and Hierarchical Networking files might be of special interest to the researcher. Materials contained in them document the important transition from a monolithic computing center at the university to the distributed network system that was eventually created.
  The Merit files consist of reports on educational computing at the University of Michigan and Wayne State University. Material in the Survey files was compiled in response to a 1975 request of Charles Overberger to the UCCPU to survey the current computer planning activities for university units. The purpose of the surveys was to compile data to be used in planning and funding during the following five years. Of special interest in the materials generated by UCCPU'S Subcommittees are those which pertain to minicomputers, computer ethics, and copyright. Such materials document issues of concern to users of the university's computer facilities.
  - Acquisition Criteria Policy 1973 (Box 1)
  - Ad Hoc Computing Advisory Committee 1964 (Box 1)
  - Committee Rosters 1968-1973, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Computer Requests
    - Hardware 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - Minicomputers
      - March 1976-June 1977 (Box 1)
      - July 1977-August 1977 (Box 1)
    - Reports
      - 1-6 1971-1973 (Box 1)
      - 7-16 1971-1973 (Box 1)
      - 17-19 1971-1973 (Box 1)
      - 20-33 1971-1973 (Box 1)
      - 34 1973 (Box 1)
      - 35 1973, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - 36-42 1974-1975 (Box 1)
      - 43 1975, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 44 1975 (Box 1)
      - 45-47 1975 (Box 1)
  - Computing Center
    - General 1968 (Box 1)
    - Determination of Charge Rates for Computational Services October 1976 (Box 1)
    - Status Report 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - User's Report 1973 (Box 1)
    - Utilization of the Computational Facility (Box 2)
      - July 1975-June 1976 (Box 2)
      - July 1976-June 1977 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - 1965-1966 (Box 2)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 2)
    - 1968-1975 (Box 2)
    - 1975 (Box 2)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - 1976 (Box 2)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - 1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Data Systems Center Reports
    - 19731975 (Box 2)
    - 19761977 (Box 2)
  - Dearborn
    - Administrative Data Processing June 1976 (Box 2)
    - Analysis of U-M Dearborn Computing 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - Benchmarks 1976 (Box 2)
    - Preliminary Report November 1975 (Box 2)
    - Proposal Status Report 1976 (Box 2)
    - Survey part I 1976 (Box 2)
    - Survey part II 1976 (Box 2)
  - Flint Proposal I 1974 (Box 2)
  - Flint Proposal II 1974 (Box 2)
  - Health Services System Automation Project Definition 1975 (Box 2)
  - Hierarchical Computing At The U of M, Report 1976-1979 (Box 2)
  - Hierarchical Networking (Box 2)
  - Hospital Data Systems Center
    - Resource Planning 1976 (Box 2)
    - Status Report 1977 (Box 2)
    - Supplemental Information 1976 (Box 3)
  - Merit
    - General 1974, 1976, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Computers and Education at Wayne State University 1976 (Box 3)
    - Educational Computing at the U of M: A Survey of Activities and Resources 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    - University Computer Policy 1973 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Interuniversity Committee on Information Systems 1971 (Box 3)
  - Minicomputers
    - Report Correspondence 1977 (Box 3)
    - Survey 1975 (Box 3)
  - Minutes
    - 1965-1967 (Box 3)
    - 1968 (Box 3)
    - 1969 (Box 3)
    - 1970 (Box 3)
    - 1971 (Box 3)
    - 1972 (Box 3)
    - 1973, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1974, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 1975, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - 1976, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - 1977, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - National Science Foundation Grant Request 1978 (Box 4)
  - Nordby, Gordon, "Closing the Gap between University Administrators and Computer Center Management," 1978 (Box 4)
  - Office of Administrative Systems Planning 1974, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Policy Proposals Reports 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - Policy 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - Projection Of U of M Computer Needs And Demands For The Next 5 Years 1968 (Box 4)
  - Small Computer Survey 1975 (Box 4)
  - Software Policy 1974-1976 (Box 4)
  - Special Computational Services and Facilities Report 1968 (Box 4)
  - Subcommittees
    - ARPA Network 1973 (Box 4)
    - Computer Ethics 1979 (Box 4)
    - Computer Software Distribution 1974 (Box 4)
    - Copyright 1973-1974 (Box 4)
    - Instructional Uses 1972 (Box 4)
    - Minicomputers 1973-1974 (Box 4)
    - MTS/OS 1974 (Box 4)
    - Organization 1967 (Box 4)
  - Surveys
    - Architecture 1976 (Box 4)
    - Business Administration 1975 (Box 4)
    - Dentistry 1975 (Box 4)
    - Education 1975 (Box 4)
    - Engineering 1976 (Box 4)
    - Law 1975 (Box 4)
    - Library Science 1977 (Box 4)
    - Literature, Science, and the Arts 1976 (Box 4)
    - Medicine 1975 (Box 4)
    - Mental Health Research Institute 1977 (Box 4)
    - Music 1975 (Box 4)
    - Natural Resources 1976 (Box 4)
    - Nursing 1976 (Box 4)
    - Planning 1975-1977 (Box 4)
    - Pharmacy 1975 (Box 4)
    - Public Health 1976 (Box 4)
    - Rackham 1977 (Box 4)
    - Social Work 1977 (Box 4)
    - TV 1974 (Box 4)
- EDUCOM Files
  The EDUCOM Files series (.5 linear feet) documents Gordon Nordby's participation in the organization from 1967 to 1979. Nordby was active on the nominating committee in 1976. He was also active in meeting planning and on the membership committee in 1979. Included in the materials is a paper he delivered at a 1979 conference. His paper was entitled "Planning for Computer Resources at a Large University" and explores work done by the UCCPU in 1977.
  - General 1967-1969 (Box 4)
  - Bylaws 1968 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence
    - 1970-1975 (Box 4)
    - 1974-1978 (Box 4)
    - 1979 (Box 4)
  - Edunet 1979 (Box 4)
  - Implementing Planning for Instructional Computing 1979 (Box 4)
  - Meeting Planning 1979 (Box 4)
  - Membership Committee 1979 (Box 4)
  - Nominating Committee 1976 (Box 4)
  - "Planning for Computer Resources at a Large University," (by Nordby) 1979 (Box 4)
  - Preliminary Proposal To Conduct An In-depth Study Of Computer Resources For Networking 1973 (Box 4)
  - Survey 1970 (Box 4)
  - University Computer Networks 1973 (Box 4)